<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="./c74ref.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>

<c74object name="lilypond" module="max" category="UI, Notation">

	<digest>
		Engrave music notation with LilyPond
	</digest>

	<description>
		Use the <o>lilypond</o> object to engrave music notation with GNU
		LilyPond and draw it in the patcher. Supply the notation as LilyPond
		source text with the <m>set</m> or <m>read</m> message, and the object
		renders it to vector graphics and resizes the box to fit. LilyPond is
		not bundled: an existing installation is located automatically, or
		pointed to with the <at>lilypondpath</at> attribute.
	</description>

	<discussion>
		The object does not bundle LilyPond; it drives a separately installed
		lilypond binary as a subprocess. Install LilyPond yourself (for example
		with "brew install lilypond" or from lilypond.org), then either let
		<at>autofind</at> locate it or set <at>lilypondpath</at> explicitly. Use
		<m>getpath</m> to confirm which binary is active. Notation is rendered on
		a background thread and redrawn automatically whenever the source or a
		display attribute changes, so rapid edits stay responsive.
	</discussion>

	<!--METADATA-->
	<metadatalist>
		<metadata name="author">Isabel Kaspriskie</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">UI</metadata>
		<metadata name="tag">notation</metadata>
	</metadatalist>

	<!--INLETS-->
	<inletlist>
		<inlet id="0" type="anything">
			<digest>set or read LilyPond source</digest>
		</inlet>
	</inletlist>

	<!--OUTLETS-->
	<outletlist>
	</outletlist>

	<!--ARGUMENTS-->
	<objarglist>
	</objarglist>

	<!--MESSAGES-->
	<methodlist>
		<method name="set">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="source" optional="0" type="list" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>
				Set the LilyPond source text
			</digest>
			<description>
				Joins the message arguments into the LilyPond source and
				re-renders. Suitable for short snippets without backslash
				commands, for example <m>set</m> { c' d' e' f' g' }. A Max
				message box cannot preserve the backslash, brace, or quote
				characters used by most LilyPond input, so use <m>read</m> for
				non-trivial scores.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="read">
			<arglist>
				<arg name="filename" optional="1" type="symbol" />
			</arglist>
			<digest>
				Load LilyPond source from a file
			</digest>
			<description>
				Reads the named .ly file, located on the Max search path, and
				re-renders. This is the preferred way to supply scores that use
				backslash commands, which a message box cannot carry.
			</description>
		</method>
		<method name="getpath">
			<digest>
				Report the active LilyPond binary path
			</digest>
			<description>
				Posts the path of the lilypond binary that would be used for the
				next render to the Max console. Useful for confirming which
				installation is active when <at>lilypondpath</at> is empty and
				<at>autofind</at> is resolving the binary automatically.
			</description>
		</method>
	</methodlist>

	<!--ATTRIBUTES-->
	<attributelist>
		<attribute name="lilypondpath" get="1" set="1" type="symbol" size="1">
			<digest>
				Path to the LilyPond binary
			</digest>
			<description>
				Absolute path to the lilypond executable used for rendering.
				When empty and <at>autofind</at> is enabled, common install
				locations are probed automatically: Homebrew
				(/opt/homebrew/bin/lilypond, /usr/local/bin/lilypond), the
				official relocatable app (/Applications/LilyPond.app), MacPorts,
				and finally $PATH. Set this to use a specific binary regardless
				of what auto-find would discover. The discovered path is written
				back to this attribute after the first successful render, so it
				is visible in the Inspector.
			</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="autofind" get="1" set="1" type="int" size="1">
			<digest>
				Auto-find the LilyPond binary
			</digest>
			<description>
				When enabled (the default), probes common install locations for a
				lilypond binary whenever <at>lilypondpath</at> is empty. Disable
				to suppress discovery and require an explicit path.
			</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="size" get="1" set="1" type="float64" size="1">
			<digest>
				Pixels per staff-space
			</digest>
			<description>
				Controls how large the notation appears, expressed as the number
				of screen pixels per staff-space (the gap between two adjacent
				staff lines). The default is 8.
			</description>
		</attribute>
		<attribute name="margin" get="1" set="1" type="float64" size="1">
			<digest>
				Margin around the notation in pixels
			</digest>
			<description>
				Padding in pixels between the rendered notation and the edges of
				the box. The box is automatically resized to fit the image plus
				this margin on all sides. The default is 8.
			</description>
		</attribute>
	</attributelist>

	<!--SEEALSO-->
	<seealsolist>
	</seealsolist>

</c74object>
